A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Newspaper Clippings 1918-1937 (Box 420)
  A. Political campaigns of 1920, 1924, and 1936: Democratic Presidential Nominating Convention of 1924. It was in this year that Carter Glass was a strong contender for the nomination. Editorials, mostly from state papers, are prolific. Carter Glass' stand on the New Deal is covered in the 1936 Presidential election.
  B. Activities of Bishop James Cannon of the Methodist church; articles on the Federal Reserve System and various banking legislation. Of special note on the latter subject if coverage of a controversy between Carter Glass and Colonel House over responsibility for getting the Federal Act written; Controversy between Carter Glass and Senator Tom Heflin over he merits and shortcomings of the system.
  C. Activities and alleged "wrong doings" of the Virginia State veterinarian, Dr. J. G. Ferneyhough and reported "meddling" in the retirement of Major General Cronkhite.
  D. Editorials on Banking and Currency legislation, including nominations of Charles S. Hamlin to Federal Reserve Board, New Bedford, Massachusetts Morning Mercury, July 3, 1926, and Carter Glass' warning against the liberalizing of regulations governing eligible paper for borrowing at the Federal Reserve banks, undated; Approximately 10 editorials, undated, referring to the announcement of J. Cloyd Byans to run as an "Independent Democrat" against Carter Glass for Congress; Editorials and articles, date 1926, dealing with failure to re-elect Dr. J. G. Ferneyhough as state veterinarian and some controversy between Fenneyhough and Carter Glass; Articles giving Carter Glass' views regarding proposed McFadden National Bank Bill and Hull amendments, (dated ?); Reports of speech by Carter Glass against proposed Hange-McNary Farm Bill, 1926; Reports of activities of Bishop James Cannon, undated. Also editorials about the Bishop and about the so-called Cannon-Goldhurst case; " Carter Glass Denies Threat to Gold Standard." Article regarding differences of opinion between Carter Glass and Hoover administration Republicans, October 13, 1932, New York Times. Numerous other articles and editorials on the subject; Editorials regarding controversy between Carter Glass and Secretary of Treasury Mills prior to national election, undated; Reports of Carter Glass' denouncement of Edwin R. Seligman's story that Paul M. Warburg was responsible for the reserve and note issue provisions of the Federal Reserve Act, 1927; Published letter from Carter Glass on the matter; Perhaps one hundred or more editorials and comments concerning the political activities of Bishop James Cannon, the Senate's inquiry into the disposition of money contributed to him for use in political campaigns, etc.; Many editorials regarding Bishop Cannon's fight for prohibition and accounts of attempts to make him a martyr, mostly undated, but appears to have been during and after the Bishop's anti-Smith campaign in 1928; Accounts of Carter Glass' attack of a book by Professor Seymour of Yale in which the latter implied that Colonel House was responsible for the Federal Reserve Act; Many editorial comments on the controversy between Carter Glass an House (ca. 1927); Many articles and editorials concerning Carter Glass' position in the 1936 Presidential election and speeches made by him assailing some New Deal policies, especially a controversial speech made in Ashland at Randolph Macon College; Editorials regarding the possibility and probability of Carter Glass for Democratic presidential nominee in the 1924 election. There are probably upwards of 100 such units, some of which speculate heavily on the outcome of the convention. McAdoo also mentioned often; New York Times article reviewing first ten months of Harding's administration, dated 1922; Miscellaneous clippings having to do with alleged local political manipulation by certain people and of various other subjects. The number of articles on any one of these subjects is small; Sports articles, medical articles and those of a religious nature; Newspaper coverage of a speech by Carter Glass in Atlanta at the National Association of Credit Men, undated; Speech included praises of farm credit legislation and advice to farmers; Account of Carter Glass speech to Masons Convention in which he attacked attempts to lower the bars of immigration, undated; Editorials regarding the ratification of a peace treaty with Germany. Much attention given to the part "former President Woodrow Wilson " will play in the affair, undated; About 10 or 15 accounts of a great tribute paid to "former President Woodrow Wilson " on the fifth anniversary of the armistice signing. Carter Glass evidently made a speech at the occasion, undated; Articles dealing with charges by Major General Cronkhite that the Army had tampered with the records of his son who was killed during Army rifle practice; Accounts of an order from the War Department forcing the General into retirement and Congressional investigation of these incidents; Several editorials dealing with a speech in defense of the Federal Reserve System by Carter Glass, 1922. The speech seems to have been in reply to Senator Tom Heflin's ( Alabama ) criticism of the system; About 20 or 30 articles dealing with the appointment by President Harding of a man to succeed Warren G. Harding as Governor of the Federal Reserve Board, 1922; Charges of the administration's advisors "playing politics" in the matter; Articles in which John Skelton Williams, one time Comptroller of the Currency, expresses opposition to increasing interest rates on business loans and clears up misunderstanding about his plan for "calling in war borrowings," no date; Scattered articles dealing with Carter Glass' stand on the British Debt Refunding Bill which was evidently being debated in the Senate in 1923. Accounts are included of a "very stirring" defense of the Bill by Carter Glass on the Senate floor; At least 25 articles and editorials commenting on a speech by Carter Glass on the Senate floor in which he took President Coolidge to task after Coolidge had criticized the Senate in the way it was handling certain investigations; Assorted reports of speeches on banking made by bankers at various conferences and meetings for bankers. Most of them deal with the merits and shortcomings of the Federal Reserve System, dated for the most part in the early 1920's; Assorted reports of speeches made on the League of Nations. For instance, on by Lord Robert Cecil of England. Mostly undated; Report of passage of Kellogg-Wadsworth bill by the Senate. The bill is an amendment which will allow states to impose the same tax on national banks as is imposed on state banks, date 1923; Several articles reporting a controversy in Bedford, Virginia, over the appointment of an evidently unpopular postmaster in the city by President Harding. Former Congressman Slemp was a major figure in the controversy.
- Newspaper Clippings 1913-1937 (Box 421)
  A. Approximately 450 clippings concerning the contest between Carter Glass and A. James for the position of National Committeeman in 1916; Many articles and editorials discussing Bishop James Cannon; Clippings relating to the Supreme Court Packing and to Carter Glass' attitude toward various aspects of the New Deal legislation and administration.
  B. Clippings covering the following topics: Speech by Carter Glass in support of the Federal Reserve Act, 1913; Editorial on various aspects of Federal Reserve policy including par check clearance, national clearing system, "overissue" of Federal Reserve notes in 1916, Carter Glass -Borah amendment to Home Loan Bank Bill, Member Bank Reserves; Editorial on Farm-Land Bank Bill sponsored by Carter Glass; Carter Glass' speech opposing Federal aid, 1934; Carter Glass' opposition to Haugen Bill; Carter Glass' activities in 1936 Presidential election; ca. 40 articles concerning Carter Glass' stand on prohibition and its relationship to the 1928 Presidential election; ca. 60 clippings on Carter Glass' attack on "The Intimate Papers of Colonel House," editorials and articles relating to the dispute between Carter Glass and Seymour over the origin of the Federal Reserve Act, and many book reviews of Carter Glass' An Adventure in Constructive Finance; Editorials on Carter Glass' stand concerning the powers of the Federal Reserve Board to control the discount rate, 1927; Several articles by Arthur D. Howden Smith on "How the Federal Reserve System Came Into Being."
- Miscellaneous correspondence, especially regarding attempts to assure the retirement of Carter Glass from the Senate 1928-1945 (Box 422)
  A. Letters relating to anticipated biographies of Woodrow Wilson: Request from the Library of Congress for the letters held by Carter Glass from President Woodrow Wilson; A refusal; Request for photostatic copies of the letters.
  B. Letters and reports concerning the settlement of war claims with Germany.
  C. Letters between Rixey Smith and Douglas S. Freeman in June, 1945, attempting to insure the validity of the pairing of Carter Glass' vote on the ratification of the San Francisco treaty.
  D. Letters, telegrams, newspaper articles, etc. relating to the attempts to assure the retirement of Carter Glass from the Senate in 1945 and 1946. Sentiment is expressed on both sides of the question. Carter Glass took no steps toward retirement.
  E. Statement sent by Carter Glass to Charles S. Hamlin, a member of the Federal Reserve Board, opposing either joint or separate action on the part of the Board or the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation to lower interest rates on time and savings deposits for both member and non-member banks. Carter Glass seriously questions the ability of government employees to regulate business and banking affairs.
  F. Correspondence between Carter Glass in Lynchburg and Rixey Smith in Washington: Rixey Smith notes his failure to find any letters on file to H. Parker Willis or E. E. Garrison, referring to Garrison; Letter to Rixey Smith, April 1, 1929, in which Carter Glass mentions preparation of replies to statements by Robert L. Owen and Samuel Untermeyer.
  G. Letter from recently defeated Senator P. T. Gore on November 7, 1936, and a reply by Carter Glass, concerning the wisdom of foregoing the chairmanship of the Appropriations Committee and retaining the chair of the Subcommittee on Banking and Currency.
  H. Proposed resolution for the Democratic Party of Virginia, instructing delegates to the National Convention to vote for renomination of Franklin D. Roosevelt.
  I. Letters to Carter Glass from Senator Harry F. Byrd.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1924-1940 (Box 423)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence, alphabetically arranged, including correspondence with Bernard M. Baruch, William E. Borah, Harry F. Byrd, Carl Hayden, Hugh S. Johnson, Thomas McAdams, William G. McAdoo, M. H. McIntyre, G. Walter Napp, James K. Vardman, H. Parker Willis, Richard Whaley; Folder of correspondence with John Daniels, 1901-1902.
  B. Letters from McAdams and Vardman concern appointments to the Federal Reserve Board of Governors.